<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects on Sara Zan</title><link>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/</link><description>Recent content in projects on Sara Zan</description><generator>Custom Script</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Jupyter Chat Widget</title><link>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/jupyter-chat-widget/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/jupyter-chat-widget/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;For my workshop at the &lt;a href="https://summit.ai" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Agentic AI Summit&lt;/a&gt; I vibe-coded this small Jupyter Notebook widget on top of ipywidgets&amp;lt;8.0.0, for easy compatibility with Colab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install it with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="codehilite"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;pip install jupyter-chat-widget
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href="https://www.zansara.dev/jupyter-chat-widget/"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://github.com/ZanSara/jupyter-chat-widget" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Single Page Helpers</title><link>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/single-page-helpers/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/single-page-helpers/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Simon Willison's collection&lt;/a&gt;, I am also building a small collection of small helpers for common tasks that I usually get done using some free web tool. In this collection I list a series of webpages, each completely self-sufficient, that can be used to perform a basic task like cropping an image, generating a QR code, or visualizing timezones. All the tools are &lt;a href="https://github.com/ZanSara/single-page-helpers" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;open-source&lt;/a&gt;, so feel free to copy them for your own personal use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find them here: &lt;a href="/single-page-helpers"&gt;Single Page Helpers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Guess Who</title><link>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/guess-who/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/guess-who/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;LLMs nowadays are headed for superintelligence, they say. They should make good tabletop game partners then, I guess?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this repo you can find a simple implementation of a Guess Who game. If you're not familiar with the rules, here they are: each player receives a character and has to guess the opponent's character name by asking one yes/no question at a time. For example: "Is your character blonde?" or "Does your character have glasses?". Whoever guesses the opponent's character first wins. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very simple game that should be within the understanding of any multimodal language model, right? &lt;a href="/guess-who/"&gt;Try for yourself&lt;/a&gt; to find out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also find the game on &lt;a href="https://github.com/ZanSara/guess-who" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Contributions of all kinds are welcome 🙇&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>L-systems</title><link>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/l-systems/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/l-systems/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In order to find a quick way to design images for my more abstract posts, I figured that an &lt;a href="http://paulbourke.net/fractals/lsys/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;L-system&lt;/a&gt; generator could help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find it here: &lt;a href="/L-systems"&gt;L-systems generator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kudos to the original developer anvaka, whose work you can find &lt;a href="https://anvaka.github.io/lsystem" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Real Life Subtitles</title><link>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/real-life-subtitles/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/real-life-subtitles/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever struggled to listen to a native speaker of the language you're learning and wished you could see subtitles in real life as well?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Real Life Subtitles, the problem is solved ✨ Just open &lt;a href="/real-life-subtitles/"&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;, insert your &lt;a href="https://deepgram.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Deepgram&lt;/a&gt; API key, press the Listen button and enjoy your realtime transcriptions!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you want to experiment, you can &lt;a href="https://github.com/ZanSara/real-life-subtitles" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;fork it on GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and make your own.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Intentional</title><link>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/intentional/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/intentional/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/intentional-ai/intentional/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Intentional&lt;/a&gt; is an open-source framework to build reliable chatbots that actually do what you expect from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pure LLM-based chatbots are very hard to control: when a lot of very specific instructions are pushed into their system prompt, their performance will get worse and worse the more instructions you add. These bots will work very well on small demos, but don't scale to real use cases, where you may need the bot to follow a very specific set of workflows depending on the situation it find itself in, without improvising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intentional introduces a new way of prompting the LLM in a way that gives the developer full control on the conversation at scale while retaining the  smooth conversational skills of the LLM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intentional is still in its very early stages: &lt;a href="https://github.com/intentional-ai/intentional/issues" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;get in touch&lt;/a&gt; if you want to give any feedback or contribute!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Haystack</title><link>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/haystack/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/haystack/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://haystack.deepset.ai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Haystack&lt;/a&gt; is an &lt;a href="https://github.com/deepset-ai/haystack" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;open-source&lt;/a&gt; end-to-end framework that allows you to build applications powered by LLMs, Transformer models, vector search and more. Whether you want to perform retrieval-augmented generation (RAG), document search, question answering, or build agent-based workflows, Haystack can orchestrate state-of-the-art embedding models and LLMs into pipelines to build end-to-end NLP applications and solve your use case. Haystack has also an active &lt;a href="https://discord.com/invite/xYvH6drSmA" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Discord&lt;/a&gt; community you can join to learn more about the framework and get help if you face problems. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early 2024 Haystack published a &lt;a href="https://haystack.deepset.ai/release-notes/2.0.0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;major release (2.0)&lt;/a&gt;, which was a full redesign of the framework. During my time at &lt;a href="https://www.deepset.ai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;deepset&lt;/a&gt; leading this redesign has been one of my major accomplishments.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Demos and notebooks</title><link>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/demos/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/demos/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I often write small demos and Python notebooks to illustrate the concepts explained in more technical blog posts and talks. Here is a collection of some of these notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jan. 26, 2026: &lt;a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1YVN5GrmZMM7qpI-dbeV-HIYig9XoSk6W?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;From RAG to AI Agents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oct. 29th, 2024: &lt;a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1CUX7JRYMU1MEJBZ6lWMg5EThPew19Zjs?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;How to Build a Reliable Voice Bot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oct. 1st, 2024: &lt;a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/11aOq-43wEWhSlxtkdXEAwPEarC0IQ3eN?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Who has the best RAG?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sep. 18th, 2024: &lt;a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1VMgK3DcVny_zTtAG_V3QSSdfSFBWAgmb?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Controlling LLM Translations of Invariant Elements with RAG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dec. 15th, 2023: &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/ZanSara/6075d418c1494e780f7098db32bc6cf6" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Optimizing LLMs with Retrieval Augmented Generation and Haystack 2.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nov. 9th, 2023: &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/ZanSara/0907a8f3ae19f62998cc061ed6e8ce53" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Haystack 2.0: The World of Web RAG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nov. 5th, 2023: &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/ZanSara/ba7efd241c61ccfd12ed48195e23bb34" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Haystack 2.0: Indexing data for RAG applications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oct. 27th, 2023: &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/ZanSara/0af1c2ac6c71d0a723c179cc6ec1ac41" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Haystack 2.0: RAG Pipelines from scratch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oct. 25th, 2023: &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/ZanSara/5975901eea972c126f8e1c2341686dfb" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Haystack 2.0: RAG Pipelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oct. 7th, 2023: &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/ZanSara/9e8557830cc866fcf43a2c5623688c74" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Multimodal Retriever: a live coding demo&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Brekeke</title><link>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/brekeke/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/brekeke/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;With the rise of more and more powerful LLMs, I am experimenting with different ways to interact with them in ways that don't necessarily involve a laptop, a keyboard or a screen. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I codenamed all of these experiments "Brekeke", the sound frogs make in Hungarian (don't ask why). The focus of these experiments is mostly small home automation tasks and run on a swarm of Raspberry Pis.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>ZanzoCam</title><link>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/zanzocam/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/zanzocam/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Main website: https://zanzocam.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ZanzoCam is a low-power, low-frequency camera based on Raspberry Pi, designed to operate autonomously in remote locations and under harsh conditions. It was designed and developed between 2019 and 2021 for &lt;a href="https://www.cai.it/gruppo_regionale/gr-lombardia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;CAI Lombardia&lt;/a&gt; by a team of two people, with me as the software developer and the other responsible for the hardware design. CAI later deployed several of these devices on their affiliate huts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ZanzoCams are designed to work reliably in the harsh conditions of alpine winters, be as power-efficient as possible, and tolerate unstable network connections: they feature a robust HTTP- or FTP-based picture upload strategy which is remotely configurable from a very simple, single-file web panel. The camera software also improves on the basic capabilities of picamera to take pictures in dark conditions, making ZanzoCams able to shoot good pictures for a few hours after sunset. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The camera is highly configurable: photo size and frequency, server address and protocol, all the overlays (color, size, position, text and images) and several other parameters can be configured remotely without the need to expose any ports of the device to the internet. They work reliably without the need for a VPN and at the same time are quite secure by design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ZanzoCams mostly serve CAI and the hut managers for self-promotion, and help hikers and climbers assess the local conditions before attempting a hike. Pictures taken for this purposes are sent to &lt;a href="https://www.rifugi.lombardia.it/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;RifugiLombardia&lt;/a&gt;, and you can see many of them &lt;a href="https://www.rifugi.lombardia.it/territorio-lombardo/webcam" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;at this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it has also been used by glaciologists to monitor glacier conditions, outlook and extension over the years. &lt;a href="https://www.servizioglaciologicolombardo.it/webcam-3" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Here you can see their webcams&lt;/a&gt;, some of which are ZanzoCams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the latest picture from &lt;a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/PwdVC82VHwdPZJDE6" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Rifugio M. Del Grande - R. Camerini&lt;/a&gt;, the test location for the original prototype:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ZanzoCam of Rifugio M. Del Grande - R. Camerini" src="https://webcam.rifugi.lombardia.it/rifugio/00003157/pictures/image__0.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is one of the cameras serving a local glaciology research group, &lt;a href="https://www.servizioglaciologicolombardo.it/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Servizio Glaciologico Lombardo&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ZanzoCam of M. Disgrazia" src="https://webcam.rifugi.lombardia.it/rifugio/90003157/pictures/image__0.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these cameras are fully solar-powered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ZanzoCam is fully open-source: check the &lt;a href="https://github.com/ZanzoCam?view_as=public" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. Due to this decision of open-sourcing the project, I was invited by &lt;a href="https://portale.unipv.it/it" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Università di Pavia&lt;/a&gt; to hold a lecture about the project as part of their &lt;a href="http://hsw2021.gnudd.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;"Hardware and Software Codesign"&lt;/a&gt;. Check out the slides of the lecture &lt;a href="talks/zanzocam-pavia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>CAI Sovico's Website</title><link>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/booking-system/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.zansara.dev/projects/booking-system/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Main website: https://www.caisovico.it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since my bachelor studies I have maintained the IT infrastructure of an alpine hut, &lt;a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/PwdVC82VHwdPZJDE6" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Rifugio M. Del Grande - R. Camerini&lt;/a&gt;. I count this as my first important project, one that people, mostly older and not very tech savvy, depended on to run a real business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The website went through several iterations as web technologies evolved, and well as the type of servers we could afford. Right now it features minimal HTML/CSS static pages, plus a reservations system written on a PHP 8 / MySQL backend with a vanilla JS frontend. It also includes an FTP server that supports a couple of &lt;a href="/projects/zanzocam/"&gt;ZanzoCams&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href="http://www.meteoproject.it/ftp/stazioni/caisovico/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;weather monitoring station&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>